[MUSIC]
[음악]
We're gonna assume that no labels are provided.
라벨이 주어지지 않았다고 가정합니다
And we're gonna aim to infer groups of related articles which are Clusters.
클러스터라는 관련 기사 그룹을 추론해내는 걸 목표로 합니다
Here the input is gonna be a vector.
입력은 벡터가 되겠지요
So every observation that we're plotting here is our word count vector.
여기 그려져있는 모든 샘플은 단어수 벡터입니다
And in this case, we're just looking at a very simple example with a vocabulary that
어휘에 단어 두 개밖에 없는 간단한 예를
only has two words.
보고 있지만요
So we have a vector, we have word 1 and word 2.
벡터가 있고 단어 1과 단어 2가 있죠
And this axis here is word 2 and this axis is word 1.
이 축은 단어 2고 이 축은 단어 1이에요
Of course, remember that in reality we tend to have very large vocabularies and
물론 현실에선 어휘량이 아주 많아서
we have these big high dimensional vectors.
고차원 벡터를 다루게 되지요
So, when we're plotting our observations, they're really in this high dimensional
고차원 공간에 샘플 그리기 어렵기 때문에
space but for visualization, let's just look at this 2D representation.
시각화를 위해 단순화된 2차원 공간을 보도록 하죠
So we have a whole bunch of documents here, all represented
수많은 문서가
by their word counts over these two different words in the vocabulary.
어휘에서 두 단어 벡터로 표현되어 있습니다
Okay, so that's the input to a clustering algorithm, and
이게 클러스터링 알고리즘의 입력이고
output is gonna be cluster labels.
출력은 클러스터 라벨이에요
And so what I mean is that this observation and
이 샘플을 포함한 여기 모든 샘플에는
all of these observations here, [SOUND] all of these get labeled as red.
빨간색 라벨이 붙죠
So maybe they get applied, some cluster label one.
클러스터 라벨 1이라고 붙이죠
So let's just call this.
그냥 그렇게 부르겠습니다
Cluster 1.
클러스터 1
So for every document, it's gonna get some label.
모든 문서에 라벨이 붙습니다
So that'll be labelled one.
이건 라벨이 1이 될 거고요
Then all of these observations here they're gonna get some other label.
여기 모든 샘플엔 다른 라벨이 붙을 겁니다
And let's assume that this is cluster 2.
이건 클러스터 2라고 하지요
So this observation gets the label 2.
이쪽 샘플에 라벨 2를 붙여 주고요
And all of these observations here would get the label 3.
이쪽 샘플에는 라벨 3이 붙습니다
So that's gonna be the output of this algorithm.
이 알고리즘의 결과값이 되겠죠
And maybe what you could do is post facto,
이제 과거로 소급해서
you could go through and look at some articles in cluster 1 and
클러스터 1의 기사를 보고
you could say that, this cluster is really a cluster about sports.
이 클러스터가 스포츠에 관한 것인지 확인할 수 있겠죠
And I just wanna write down explicitly that this label is provided post facto.
여기 이 라벨은 소급해서 붙였다는 표시를 해둬야 겠네요
Okay, well this is an example
이게 비지도 학습의 예인데
of an unsupervised learning task because we're operating without any labels.
라벨 없이 결과를 도출했기 때문이에요
All we have are observations and
가진 것이라고는 샘플이고
we're trying to uncover some structure in these observations.
이 샘플 아래 잠재된 구조를 밝히려고 할 뿐입니다
So, again, just to reiterate, the input are our word count vectors and
다시 한 번 말하자면 입력은 단어수 벡터이고
the output is, for every document in the corpus,
출력은 말뭉치의 모든 문서에 대한
we're gonna associate some cluster label with that document.
클러스터 라벨입니다
Okay, well, what defines a cluster?
클러스터의 범위 설정을 어떻게 하지요?
Well, every cluster is defined by a cluster center, so
모든 클러스터는 클러스터 중심을
maybe I'll mark the cluster centers with Xs.
기준으로 설정되기 때문에 X로 표시하죠
And then there's the shape to the cluster, and
다음으로 클러스터의 형태인데
these ellipses are representing the shapes of each of these clusters.
이 타원이 각 클러스터의 형태를 나타냅니다
And so, when we think about whether this observation,
그런데 이 샘플을 보면
this observation here should be assigned to the green cluster, or the red cluster.
초록색 클러스터에 속해야 하는지 빨간색 클러스터에 속해야 하는지 확실하지 않습니다
What we're doing is we're looking at how similar
이 기사가 클러스터의 형태를 기반으로
this article is, to other articles based on the shape of this cluster.
다른 기사에 얼마나 유사한지를 보는 겁니다
So we score every observation
모든 샘플의 점수를 클러스터 중심과
based on the cluster center as well as the shape of that cluster.
클러스터의 형태 기반으로 매깁니다
And in this case, because this cluster is, has this kind of oblong-skewed shape,
이 클러스터는 일종의 찌그러진 직사각형 형태를 띄고 있으므로
it actually gets assigned to the green cluster instead of this red cluster.
빨간색 클러스터가 아닌 초록색 클러스터에 속하게 됩니다
But another approach which is very common
흔하게 쓰이는 또 다른 접근법은
is instead of looking at the shape of the cluster, we just look at cluster centers.
클러스터의 형태가 아니라 클러스터 중심만을 봅니다
So we just measure the distance of this observation, so
그리고 샘플의 거리를 계산해
maybe let me change colors here, so this alternative approach here.
잠깐 색을 바꿀게요, 이 접근법으로는
As we would just look at the distance of this observation to
초록색, 빨간색 클러스터로의 거리만을
the green cluster center versus the red cluster center.
보게 됩니다
And in this case, it would be very challenging to decide whether that article
그럴 경우 이 기사가 초록색 클러스터에 속하는지
should go with the green cluster or the red cluster.
빨간색 클러스터에 속해는지 알기가 매우 어렵지요
But, there are other cases like this observation here where pretty obvious
하지만 여기 이 샘플의 경우 이 기준에 따르면
with this metric that it would get assigned to this red cluster.
아주 명백하게 빨간색 클러스터에 속하겠죠